Finding Aid for St. Peter's Danish Evangelical Lutheran Church (Detroit, Mich.) records, 1880-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Peter's Danish Evangelical Lutheran Church (Detroit, Mich.) records 1880-1980
St. Peter's Danish Evangelical Lutheran Church (Detroit, Mich.)
86784 Ba 2; Ba Outsize
Histories, minutes of meetings, treasurer's reports and minutes; records of youth and women's organizations; and yearbooks and church newspaper.
5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group cam from Cana Evangelical Lutheran Church (donor no. 6676 ) and from Chris Feddersen (donor no. 4785 )
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
St. Peter's Danish Evangelical Lutheran Church developed out of the efforts of Scandinavians in Detroit to have their own church. As early as 1874, monthly services were held for Scandinavian Americans and those Scandinavians who were newly immigrated. This small group known as St. Peter's Scandinavian Evangelical Lutheran Church even built its own church building in 1876. There were some early growing pains as the group broke up in 1877, only to be reformed in 1880 and formally organized on October 2, 1882 as St. Peter's Danish Evangelical Lutheran Church.
The records of St. Peter's Danish Evangelical Lutheran Church, some of which are in Danish, have been organized into the following series: History / Organizational; Minute books of meetings; Financial records and miscellanea; Church organizations; Publications; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Danish Americans--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.); Lutheran Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Women--Michigan--Detroit--Societies and clubs.; Youth--Michigan--Detroit.; Women--Religious life--Michigan--Detroit.; Youth--Religious life--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Danish Americans--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.; Fremtids Vel.; Lutheran Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Lutherans, Danish--Michigan.; St. Peter's Danish Evangelical Lutheran Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- History / Organizational
  - Histories 1907, 1957, circa 1963, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Record Book 1901; including history, constitution, and membership list (Box 1)
  - Record book: include history, budget 1961-1980, Council staff, 1961-1976, Education, 1978-1980, Evangelism, 1960s, Miscellaneous, 1958-1980, 1 folders (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents, including material on land purchases, incorporation, and annual reports (Box 1)
  - Constitutions and By-laws (Box 1)
  - Church Correspondence 1939-1945 (Box 1)
  - Church Correspondence 1946-1958 (Box 1)
  - Letters from church to members, mimeograph (Box 1)
  - Church correspondence re. calling of pastor 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Congregational Profile 1965, 1978 (Box 1)
- Minutes of meetings
  (include congregational meetings, trustee meetings, annual meetings)
  - 1880-1898 (Box 1)
    (includes founding constitution; and listing of first members)
  - 1890-1901 (Box 1)
    (includes constitution of 1899)
  - 1901-1912 (Box 1)
  - 1912-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1936-1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945-1955 (Box 2)
  - 1955-1962 (Box 2)
  - 1961-1970 (Box 2)
  - 1970-1980 (Box 2)
- Financial records and miscellaneous
  - 1955 (Box 2)
  - Financial Reports and Minutes
    - 1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961 (Box 2)
    - 1902 (Box 2)
    - 1963 (Box 2)
    - 1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971 (Box 2)
    - 1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973 (Box 2)
    - 1974 (Box 2)
  - Minutes of Trinity Congregation 1917-1921 (Box 2)
  - Membership Lists 1964, 1965, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Church Relocation 1949-1953 (Box 2)
  - Church Construction 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - Contributions to Building Fund 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  - Dedication of new church building (Box 2)
  - Architectural blueprints of the new church (Box 3)
  - Guest book 1952-1958 (Box 3)
  - Treasurer's Records
    - 1891-1896 (Box 3)
      (in Danish)
    - 1899-1901 (Box 3)
    - 1912-1917 (with membership information) (Box 3)
  - Contributions
    - 1967 (Box 3)
    - 1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969 (Box 3)
- Church organizations
  - Youth groups
    - "Fremtids Vel" Young Peoples Society minute book 1924-1936 (Box 3)
      (in Danish until 1929)
    - "Junior Young Peoples Society" minute book 1942-1947 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous for "Fremtids Vel" 1920-1938 (Box 3)
    - "Ungdom" (newspaper from Cedar Falls, Iowa, with an article on "Fremtids Vel") (Box 3)
    - Young America-Danish Lutheran Home Circle Minutes 1924-1926 (Box 4)
  - "Kvindeforening" (Women's Organization)
    - Minutes 1897-1904 (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1914-1917 (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1928-1941 (Box 4)
    - Minutes 1941-1955 (Box 4)
      (minutes permanently changed to English on March 9, 1954)
    - Minutes 1964-1980 (Box 4)
    - Treasurer's Records
      - 1918-1925 (Box 4)
        (in Danish through 1920)
      - 1927-1934 (Box 4)
      - 1935-1942 (Box 4)
      - 1942-1948 (Box 4)
      - 1947-1952 (Box 4)
    - Membership List 1942 (Box 4)
- Publications
  - Church Yearbook
    - 1927-1928 (Box 5)
    - 1928-1929 (Box 5)
    - 1958 (Box 5)
    - 1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 5)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 5)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 5)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 5)
    - 1966 (Box 5)
    - 1967 (Box 5)
    - 1968 (Box 5)
  - Church Newspaper "Kirkebladet" (in Danish and English)
    - March 1930-1932 (Box 5)
    - 1933-1935 (Box 5)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 5)
    - 1938-1940 (Box 5)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 5)
    - 1943-1944 (Box 5)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 5)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 5)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 5)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 5)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 5)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 5)
    - January-May 1957 (Box 5)
  - Church Newspaper "The Messenger" (In English)
    - September 1957-1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960-February 1962 (Box 5)
    - 1964-1968 (Box 5)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 5)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    - 1975-June 1980 (Box 5)
  - Church service programs
    - circa 1955-1959 (Box 5)
    - August 1959 (82nd Annual Convention) (Box 5)
    - circa 1960-1962 (Box 5)
  - Danish Evangelical Lutheran Church of America
    - Newsletter: Lutheran Tidings, 1951-1960 (Box 5)
    - Pamphlet on denominational history (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Later materials (Box 5)
- Photographs and poster
  - Church interior (Catherine Street) 1889 (Box 5)
  - Church under construction (Greenfield) 1954 (Box 5)
  - Fremtids Vel: Delegates to conference 1917 (Box 5)
  - Photograph of picnic at Orchard Lake 1917 (Folder 1)
  - Poster describing goals and functions of group (Folder 1)